"Dietary Approach to Naturally
Treating Menopause Symptoms"
There is a great
variety of symptoms
suffered by women
undergoing menopause.
There are the so-called
vasomotor symptoms,
like night sweats and hot
ﬂashes, diﬃculty sleeping
or full-on insomnia, vaginal
dryness, and pain during sex,
as well as adverse effects on mood
including full-blown depression.
Might exercise help?
Exercise can certainly help with
physical and psychological quality
of life in general, but unfortunately
there was no evidence
for the eﬀects of exercise on
menopause-speciﬁc symptoms.
You know researchers are
getting desperate when they try
to see if giving people
pig placenta will help.
Spoiler alert: it doesn’t.
Well, we know oxidative stress,
which is a consequence of
excessive free oxygen radicals
or impaired antioxidant defense,
is linked not only to diseases
such as diabetes, obesity,
and cardiovascular disease,
but also menopausal
symptoms like hot flashes.
Low free oxygen radical
defense is associated with
more menopausal symptoms,
just like having a diet with more
antioxidants is associated
with fewer menopausal symptoms.
In fact, a high intake of
fruits and vegetables may delay
the onset of menopause
in the first place,
thought to be because
the presence of antioxidants
in fruits and vegetables may
counteract the adverse effects
of free radicals on the number
of functional eggs you still have
in your ovaries, whereas
a reason high meat consumption
has been related to
degenerative diseases
may not just be the
saturated fat and cholesterol,
but the pro-oxidation products
generated during their production,
storage, digestion,
and metabolism of meat.
Similarly, since a pro-
inflammatory diet has also been
associated with higher menopause-
specific somatic symptoms,
meaning like hot flashes
and sleep issues,
that would mean moving
towards a more plant-based diet
packed with anti-inflammatory
components like fiber
and away from pro-inflammatory
foods containing
saturated fat and cholesterol.
No wonder whole plant
foods intake has been
associated with fewer
menopausal symptoms.
In terms of specific foods,
poultry and skim dairy products
may be particularly bad,
whereas soy milk seemed to help.
So, women may derive benefit
from lower consumption
of poultry and skimmed dairy
and a greater consumption
of vegetables and soy milk.
You don’t really know, though...
until you put it to the test.
And indeed, women randomized
to drink soy milk reduced
their menopausal symptoms by
20 percent within 12 weeks.
No wonder that those eating
strictly plant-based diets
report less bothersome
menopausal symptoms.
Among women undergoing menopause,
vegans reported less
bothersome symptoms,
and within the diet
groups more vegetables,
and in the meat-eating group,
less ﬂesh food was associated
with less bothersome
symptoms as well.
So, eating a plant-based
diet may be helpful for women
in their menopausal transition
who prefer a natural means
to manage their symptoms,
consistent with all the other
studies demonstrating reduced
menopausal symptoms in those
consuming greater quantities of
plant-based foods and less meat.
But again, maybe
there are other reasons
healthier eaters
have fewer symptoms.
You can’t prove cause and
effect until...you guessed it.
An interventional trial to
see if changing your diet
actually reduces symptoms.
And in this study, where women
were encouraged to decrease fat
and increase fruit, vegetable,
and whole grain intake,
they were significantly
more likely to eliminate
their vasomotor symptoms like
hot flashes and night sweats
compared to the control group.
So, it’s certainly not all or nothing.
And within a plant-based
diet, those randomized
to a meat-free diet with
daily flaxseed oil, walnuts,
and almonds did better
than those randomized
to the same diet but with
daily extra-virgin olive oil.
After 16 weeks, the
vegetarian diet that was rich
in omega-3s did better reducing
vasomotor symptom frequency.
In fact, even just two teaspoons
worth of ground flaxseeds a day
alone can significantly decrease
menopausal symptoms to about
the same extent as
hormone replacement therapy,
but without the side effects.